Adja Yunkers Papers
Adja Yunkers Papers
1941-1959
Yunkers, Adja, 1900-1983.
0.25 linear ft.
Correspondence, published material, clippings, scrapbook from the Latvian-American lithographer and painter.
2707543
Biographical History
Adja Yunkers (1900-1983) was an artist and teacher known for his color woodcuts, lithographs, and abstract paintings. Born in Latvia, he studied in Europe, established a workshop in Stockholm, and eventually emigrated to the United States in 1946, where he was awarded a Guggenheim Fellowship. He taught at the Cooper Union Art School and the New School for Social Research.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Adja Yunkers Papers contains biographical material, correspondence, and printed material.
Biographical material consists of a bibliography of Junkers' publications, including essays, introductions and so on.
Correspondence consists of letters between the Yunkers and Richard and Ellen Vowles and a few incoming telegrams from museums related to exhibits.
Printed material contains scrapbooks of clippings and miscellaneous printed material, including programs, reviews, and so on in English and other languages.
Arrangement of the Collection
Material is arranged alphabetically.
Related Material
has many manuscript collections of artists, including painters, illustrators, cartoonists, and sculptors. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Painters; Yunkers, Adja, 1900-1983.; Lithography -- 20th century.; Painters -- United States -- 20th century.; Correspondence.; Clippings (information artifacts); Scrapbooks.; Painters.; Lithographers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Adja Yunkers, 1964.
Vowles letters, gift of Liz Vowles, 2014.
Inventory
- Biographical material
  - Bibliography, undated (Oversize 1)
  - Chronology, undated (Oversize 1)
  - Statement on art, 1959 (Oversize 1)
- Correspondence
  - Museums, 1946 (Oversize 1)
  - Vowles, Richard and Ellen, 1945-1958; undated (Oversize 1)
- Printed material
  - Scrapbook I, 1941-1946; programs, reviews, clippings, etc. (Oversize 1)
  - Scrapbook II, 1943-1946; programs, reviews, clippings, etc. (Oversize 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1946-1952; undated; programs, reviews, clippings, etc. (Oversize 1)